Before we wrap up the core content, here are some inclusive practice tips you can start using today.
These are small, concrete actions that make a real difference.
Tip number one: Always ask — never assume.
If you are not sure how to support someone, ask them directly.
A simple question like "How can I best assist you today?" respects their expertise about their own needs.
Tip number two: Make your space scan a habit.
Before your next shift, look at your workspace with fresh eyes.
Can someone in a wheelchair reach the counter?
Is the signage readable from five feet away?
Is there a clear path to the door?
Tip number three: Speak to the person, not their companion.
When a patient is accompanied by a support person or interpreter, direct your conversation to the patient.
Make eye contact with them.
They are the expert on their own care.
Tip number four: Offer information in more than one format.
If you are handing out a printed form, ask if the person would prefer large print, an electronic version, or verbal instructions.
These four tips connect directly to the Accessibility in Practice model — awareness, communication, environment, and response.