Now let us look at a framework you will use throughout this entire series.
It is called the Accessibility in Practice model, and it has four areas.
The first area is Awareness.
This means recognizing barriers and biases — including your own unconscious assumptions about disability.
Awareness is the starting point for every accessible interaction.
The second area is Communication.
This means adapting how you share and receive information.
It could mean offering forms in large print, using plain language, providing a sign language interpreter, or simply asking someone how they prefer to communicate.
The third area is Environment.
This means shaping inclusive physical and digital spaces.
Think about doorway widths, signage contrast, website navigation, and exam room layouts.
The environment either enables or prevents access.
The fourth area is Response.
This means acting with dignity and flexibility when someone needs something different.
It is about how you react in the moment — with respect, without judgment, and with a willingness to adapt.
These four areas work together.
Throughout this series, each guide will explore how awareness, communication, environment, and response apply to a specific disability context.