Now it is time to create your My Action Plan — your MAP.
This is a tool you will use in every guide throughout the series, and it travels with you.
Your MAP has three sections.
Stop: What is one thing you will stop doing?
Maybe it is assuming you know what someone needs.
Maybe it is walking past a barrier you have noticed but never reported.
Start: What is one thing you will start doing?
Maybe it is asking every patient how they prefer to receive information.
Maybe it is doing a workspace accessibility scan.
Continue: What is one thing you are already doing well that you want to keep doing?
Maybe you already speak directly to patients rather than their companions.
Maybe you already use plain language in your communications.
Fill in your MAP on screen.
You can also download it as a PDF to keep at your workstation.
Your MAP entries are saved to your learner profile and are private.