Here is a second scenario.
Mrs.
Rajapaksa is a 74-year-old woman with low vision.
She has arrived at a UHN hospital for a follow-up appointment in the cardiology clinic.
She is standing at a corridor intersection where three hallways meet.
The directional signs on the wall have small black text on a white background.
There is no colour coding, no tactile indicators, and no high-contrast formatting.
Mrs.
Rajapaksa is using a handheld magnifying glass to try to read the sign, but the text is too small.
Other patients and staff walk past without noticing.
You are a staff member who happens to be walking through this corridor.
You notice Mrs.
Rajapaksa looking at the sign.
What do you do?
Think about the Decision Path — Pause, Listen, Apply, Adapt, Seek Support.
Choose from the options on screen.
Remember, the best response respects her independence while offering meaningful support.