Congratulations — you have completed Guide 1: Foundations of Disability Inclusion and Accessible Design.
This guide is the foundation for the entire Accessibility First series.
The concepts you explored today — the human rights model, the Accessibility in Practice model, and the Decision Path — will appear in every guide that follows.
On screen, you can see the series progress map.
Guide 1 is now complete.
Guide 2 — Visual and Sensory Disabilities — is unlocked and ready for you whenever you are.
Thank you for investing your time in building a more accessible UHN.
Every step you take matters.
See you in Guide 2.
Total Narration Summary
| Screen | Title | Word Count | Estimated Time |
|--------|-------|------------|----------------|
| 1 | Welcome and Course Purpose | 142 | 57s |
| 2 | Learning Objectives | 117 | 47s |
| 3 | Why This Matters in Healthcare | 162 | 65s |
| 4 | Core Concept: Models of Disability | 195 | 78s |
| 5 | Accessibility in Practice Model | 189 | 76s |
| 6 | Accessibility Decision Path | 190 | 76s |
| 7 | Scenario 1: Hospital Booking | 165 | 66s |
| 8 | Scenario 2: Clinic Signage | 155 | 62s |
| 9 | Knowledge Check 1 | 85 | 34s |
| 10 | Knowledge Check 2 | 58 | 23s |
| 11 | Inclusive Practice Tips | 196 | 78s |
| 12 | Reflection Prompt | 140 | 56s |
| 13 | MAP Action Planning | 160 | 64s |
| 14 | Key Takeaways | 175 | 70s |
| 15 | Resources and References | 96 | 38s |
| 16 | Course Completion | 111 | 44s |
| **Total** | | **2,336** | **~15 min 34s** |
Voice Direction Notes
- **Pronunciation:** Use Canadian English ("centre" not "center", "colour" not "color").
Pronounce AODA as "ay-oh-dee-ay."
- **Pacing:** Slow slightly for key terms on first introduction (e.g., "human rights model," "Accessibility Decision Path").
Normal pace for narrative sections.
- **Tone Shifts:** Warmer for scenarios, more structured for framework explanations, quieter for reflection.
- **Pauses:** Honour all  markers with a 1-2 second pause.
Longer pause (2-3 seconds) before scenario choices.
References
- Statistics Canada.
(2023).
*Canadian Survey on Disability, 2022*.
Government of Canada.
- Accessibility for Ontarians with Disabilities Act, S.O.
2005, c.
11.
- United Nations.
(2006).
*Convention on the Rights of Persons with Disabilities*.
United Nations.
- University Health Network.
(2024).
*Patient experience and accessibility framework*.
UHN.