Here is a number worth knowing.
According to Statistics Canada, more than 27 percent of Canadians aged 15 and older have at least one disability.
In Ontario, that number is even higher.
That means more than one in four people who come to UHN for care may experience barriers related to disability.
And many disabilities are non-visible — you may not know someone has a disability unless they tell you.
The reality is that healthcare systems were often designed without disability in mind.
Narrow doorways, small print on intake forms, appointment booking systems that require phone calls, waiting rooms with no seating options — these are everyday barriers that affect real people.
When we remove these barriers, we do not just help people with disabilities.
We create a better experience for everyone — older adults, people recovering from surgery, caregivers with strollers, anyone navigating a stressful moment.
Accessibility benefits all of us.
And it starts with understanding.