Let us put what you have learned into practice with a scenario.
Marcus is a 45-year-old man who is Deaf.
He communicates primarily in American Sign Language — ASL.
He arrives at the outpatient reception desk at a UHN clinic for a pre-surgical consultation.
He holds up his phone, which shows a text message that reads: "I need a sign language interpreter for my appointment."
The receptionist, Lin, has not encountered this situation before.
She is not sure what to do.
The appointment is in 20 minutes.
There is no interpreter on site.
Now it is your turn.
Think about the Accessibility Decision Path.
What should Lin do?
You will see three options on screen.
Choose the one that best reflects an accessible, dignity-centred response.
After you choose, you will receive feedback explaining the strengths and limitations of each option.
Take your time.
There is no penalty for choosing an imperfect answer — this is about learning.