Let us bring it all together.
Here are the key takeaways from Guide 1.
First: Disability is best understood through the human rights model — a framework that centres full participation, dignity, and equity, not diagnosis or deficit.
Second: The Accessibility in Practice model gives you four areas to focus on — awareness, communication, environment, and response.
Every guide in this series will build on these four areas.
Third: The Accessibility Decision Path — Pause, Listen, Apply, Adapt, Seek Support — is your go-to framework for any accessibility situation.
When in doubt, start with Pause.
Fourth: Accessibility is not a special accommodation.
It is a standard of care.
It benefits everyone, and it is everyone's responsibility at UHN.
And fifth: Small actions matter.
A space scan, a question asked with respect, a form offered in a different format — these are the building blocks of an inclusive healthcare environment.
You have completed Guide 1.
Well done.
Download the job aids linked on this screen to keep these frameworks at your fingertips.