Take a moment now to reflect.
Think about a recent interaction at work — with a patient, a colleague, or a visitor.
Was there a moment where accessibility could have been handled differently?
Not necessarily a failure, but an opportunity.
On screen, you will see a text box where you can write a brief reflection.
You might consider questions like: What barriers have I noticed in my workspace that I had not thought about before?
When was the last time I asked someone how they preferred to receive information?
What is one thing I could change this week?
Your reflection is private.
It is not shared with your manager or anyone else.
This is for your own learning.
Take as much time as you need.
When you are ready, move on to the action planning screen.