How we think about disability shapes how we respond to it.
So let us look at three models that have influenced healthcare and society.
The first is the medical model.
This model treats disability as a problem located in the individual — something to be diagnosed, treated, or cured.
For decades, this was the dominant view in healthcare.
Under this model, the focus is on fixing the person.
The second is the social model.
This model shifts the focus from the person to the environment.
It says that people are disabled not by their bodies or minds, but by barriers in society — stairs instead of ramps, information only in print, attitudes that exclude.
Under this model, the focus is on fixing the barriers.
The third — and the one that guides this series — is the human rights model.
This model builds on the social model but goes further.
It says that people with disabilities have the right to full participation in every aspect of life.
It is not enough to remove barriers.
We must actively ensure inclusion, dignity, and equity.
At UHN, we use the human rights model as our foundation.
This means we do not just accommodate — we include.