When you encounter a situation involving accessibility, what do you actually do?
That is where the Accessibility Decision Path comes in.
This is a five-step framework you can use in any moment.
Step one is Pause.
Before you act, take a breath and notice what is happening.
Are you making assumptions?
Is there a barrier you had not considered?
Step two is Listen.
Hear the person in front of you.
Ask how they would like to be supported.
Do not assume you know what someone needs.
Step three is Apply.
Use what you have learned — from this series, from your training, from your experience — to respond appropriately.
Step four is Adapt.
If your first approach does not work, adjust.
Flexibility is not a sign of failure.
It is a sign of competence.
And step five is Seek Support.
If you are unsure, ask for help.
Contact your manager, reach out to Patient Relations, or consult with accessibility resources at UHN.
You do not have to have all the answers.
These five steps — Pause, Listen, Apply, Adapt, Seek Support — will come back in every guide.
They are your anchor.